Guide to the Wesley Clair Mitchell Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series IX: [X] Miscellaneous, (8 Boxes: Boxes 25-27; 41-45)
  - 1931 [n.d.]; printed 8 p; (17 copies); Bibliography of Wesley Clair Mitchell: from Bibliography of the Faculty of Political Science, Columbia University 1880-1930". (Box 26, Folder X45)
  - 1932 Jan 1; hol 8 p; "Tools of Economics"; talk to teachers of economics conference (in England). (Box 26)
  - 1932 Feb 23; hol 6 p; "Organization of Economic Teaching"; talk to economics tutors at Keble [?] College. (Box 26)
  - [1932 Mar 22?]; hol 3 p; "Economic Trends in the U.S."; talk to Harvard freshmen. (Box 26)
  - 1932 July 1; hol 6 p; "Outline made while working on Introduction to Recent Social Trends". (Box 26)
  - 1932 Oct 13; hol 11 p; copy 8 p; "Economics at the English Universities"; talk to Columbia Economics Club. (Box 26)
  - [1932 ?]; hol 3 p; suggestions for address as chairman of Section K. of AAAS. (Box 26, Folder X57)
  - [1932 ?]; hol 5 p; "International Factors in American Life"; attached - population statistics notes. (Box 26, Folder X58)
  - 1933 Jan 27; hol 2 p; copy 2 p; "Social Trends and Education"; talk to Bureau of Educational Experiments. (Box 26)
  - 1933 Feb 2; hol 9 p; copy 7 p; "Social Trends and Education"; talk at Lincoln School. (Box 26)
  - 1933 Feb 24; typed ms 20 p; "Economics Trends in the U.S."; address to Falk Foundation dinner. (Box 26)
  - (1)1933 Mar 1; hol 5 p; copy 5 p; "Social Trends and Education"; lecture to Teachers College Class. (Box 26)
  - (2)1933 Mar 1; mimeograph ms 11 p; "Recent Social Changes"; address to Teachers Colleges; with introduction by J.*. Clark and carbon letter to WCM by secretary on receipt of address copy (7/15/33). (Box 26)
  - 1933 Sep 14; hol 2 p; copy 2 p; talk on 10th anniversary of SSRC. (Box 26)
  - 1934 Apr 4; hol 4 p; copy 3 p; talk to Memorial Meeting for Harriet Johnson; attached - program. (Box 26)
  - 1934 Apr 16; hol 10 p; copy 6 p; talk on aims of education - Oxford and U.S. (Box 26)
  - (1)1934 Sep 21; hol 1 p; "Trend of Economics"; talk to honor students at University of California. (Box 26)
  - (2)1934 Sep 21; hol 4 p; "Research in the Social Sciences"; talk to Institute of Social Science, University of California. (Box 26)
  - 1934 Sep 22; hol 1 p; "Role of Crisis in Social Evolution"; talk at University of California. (Box 26)
  - 1934 Oct 4; carbon ms 4 p; "Need for Economic Education"; talk on radio. (Box 26)
  - 1934 Nov 21; hol 5 p; copy 5 p; "'Max Lerner Group'"; talk on social groups and conflicts on the U.S., Marx and Veblen. (Box 26)
  - 1934 Dec 17; mimeographed and printed, seating list and program for WCM birthday dinner. (Box 26)
  - 1934 Dec 18; 1 p; newspaper clipping on birthday dinner. (Box 26)
  - 1934 Dec 23; hol 2 p; copy excerpt 1 p; list of suggested topics for Harvard Tercentenary address; quotes by H. Brown, Woodbridge for same. (Box 26)
  - 1935 June [?]; printed 2 of review by James of Economic Essays Contributed in Honor of Wesley Clair Mitchell (Box 26)
  - 1935 Sep 7; hol 4 p; "Shawnee"; economic research organization plans, history of NB. (Box 26)
  - 1936 Apr 16; hol 4 p; talk to Memorial Meeting for James Harvey Robinson. (Box 26)
  - 1936 Jun 13; printed 1 p; review by E. Ginzberg of What Veblen Taught. (Box 26)
  - 1936 Jun 17; printed 1 p; review by S. Hook What Veblen Taught. (Box 26)
  - 1936 Dec [?]; carbon ms 5 p; "Appendix B; Note on Statistical Organization in the United States Prior to the Organization of The Central Statistical Board" [by WCM?]. (Box 26)
  - [1936 ?]; carbon ms 1 p; bibliography of WCM, 1936. (Box 26, Folder X47)
  - [1936 ?]; hol 4 p; copy 6 p; "Intelligence and the Guidance of Economic Evolution"; Harvard Tercentenary address. (Box 26, Folder X46)
  - 1937 Apr 7; hol and typed ms 4 p, printed; introduction of speakers at Academy of Political Science session on Economic and Financial Policies of the U.S.; attached - program (speakers: R. Warren, white, V?. Culbertson, Sayre). (Box 26)
  - 1937 May 11; carbon ms 3 p; copy 3 p; address on and to National Institute of Social Sciences. (Box 26)
  - 1937 July 31; printed 2 p; review by L. Lyon of 3ASM. (Box 26)
  - 1937 Sep [?]; printed 2 p; review by E.P. Brown of BASM. (Box 26)
  - [1937 ?]; carbon 1 p; WCM bibliography, 1937. (Box 26, Folder X50)
  - [1937 ?]; printed, copy 1 p; review by H. Mussey of BASA. (Box 26)
  - 1938 Dec 27; typed ms 8 p; "Scientists as Citizens"; address to AAAS meeting, Rotary Club luncheon. (Box 26)
  - 1933 Dec 29; carbon ms 10 p; copy 9 p; "Science and the State of Mind"; address to American Science Teachers Association. (Box 26)
  - 1938 Dec [?]; printed 2 p; cover of Virginia Journal of Education with WCM photograph and message on use of science. (Box 26)
  - 1939 Mar 16; hol 3 p; talk at dinner honoring Eveline L. Burns. (Box 27)
  - 1939 Mar 27 to May 15; mimeograph outline 7 p; outline of seminar 315 on imperialism; with bibliography. (Box 27)
  - 1939 Apr 25; hol 5 p; copy 3 p; talk to New School Anniversary dinner on its early history. (Box 27)
  - 1939 Apr 27; hol 5 p;2copies 5 p; "Social Unit Plan"; talk at dinner to present plan. (Box 27)
  - 1939 May 2; hol 23 p; talk on R. Lynd's Knowledge for What to Columbia Economics Club. (Box 27)
  - 1933 May 25; "Technological and Social Change"; talk to Bank Street students(3 p) (Box 27)
  - 1339 Oct 11; hol 5 p; "Impact of War on the Economy of the U.S."; talk to Columbia Economics Club. (Box 27)
  - 1953 Oct 13; hol 3 p; "What the national Bureau is and Does"; talk to Advisory Conference on Financial Research. (Box 27)
  - 1939 Oct 20; typed ms 2 p; copy 1 p; "Debt of the Social Sciences to John Dewey"; talk in honor of his 80th birthday. (Box 27)
  - 1959 Oct 21; hol 2 p; copy 2 p; "Resources for Building America"; introductory talk at John Dewey's 80th birthday Conference: conference program attached. (Box 27)
  - 1939 Nov 20; carbon ms 9 p; summary of meeting to discuss plans for University National Bureau. Committee (Box 27)
  - 1959 Dec 1; typed ms 13 p; excerpt copy 7 p; "Integration of the Social Sciences"; talk at 10th anniversary of University of Chicago Social Sciences Building; meetings program attached. (Box 27)
  - 1959 Dec 27; hol 7 p; "Public Relations of Science"; broadcast of AAAS address with introduction. (Box 27)
  - 1939 Dec 29; carbon ms 7 p; "Feeling and Thinking in Scientific Work"; talk to Pi Gamma Mu, Columbus, Ohio. (Box 27)
  - 1939 Dec [?]; [publication date]; carbon ms 5 p; "Edward Robert Anderson Seligman, 1931-1939". (Box 27)
  - [1933 ?]; typed 2 p; r/CV. bibliography for J. Dorfman. (Box 27, Folder X51)
  - [1939 ?]; typed ms 21 p; copy 17 p; series of papers: "How the National Bureau's Program is Made", "Choosing the Subjects of Research", "Estimates of National Income as a guide to Economic Reason", "Limitations on the Number of Undertakings", "Investigations should Contribute to One Another" [by WCM?] (Box 27, Folder X49)
  - 1940 May 1; hol 3 p; carbon ms 8 p; address at dinner in honor of Vladimir Simkhovitch. (Box 27)
  - 1940 Lvov 11; typed and hol and carbon ins 23 p; copy 13 p; "National Unity and Intellectual Freedom"; address to American Committee for Democracy and Intellectual Freedom". (Box 27)
  - 1941 Dec 12; hol 27 p; "Economics and the Formation of Public Policies"; talk to Columbia Economics Club. (Box 27)
  - 1940 Dec 23; hol 8 p; typed ms 6 p; "Economic Effects of the Civil War"; talk to AEA meeting. (Box 27)
  - 1942 Feb 10; typed ms 3 p; "why Keep Prices Down?" (Box 27)
  - 1942 Apr 19; hol 2 p; "Research in Industry"; talk to meeting of Universities N3 Committee. (Box 27)
  - 1942 Dec 7; carbon ms 35 p; "What Should the Ordinary Citizen Know about Economics?" (Box 27)
  - (1)1943 Feb 3; typed ms 35 p; "What Should the Ordinary Citizen Know?; about Economics?" (12/7/42 draft with comments by A.F*. Bums). (Box 27)
  - (2)1943 Feb 8; carbon ms 27 p; "What Should the Ordinary Citizen Know about Economics?" (2nd draft). (Box 27)
  - 1943 Mar/ 20; hol 10 p; "Wartime Prosperity and the Future"; talk to Bank Street students. (Box 27)
  - [1944 ?]; typed 20 p; printed 3 p; \"C'A bibliography. (Box 27, Folder X7)
  - 1945 Hay 11; hol and typed ms 23 p; copy 25 p; "Fifty Years as an Economist"; talk to Columbia Economics Club. (Box 27)
  - 1945 June 6; hol 11 p; "Regional Research"; talk at Federal Reserve Bank of Philadelphia; attached - list of those present. (Box 27)
  - 1946 Oct 15; newspaper clippings on National Council of American-Soviet Friendship sponsors. (Box 27)
  - 1946,0ct[nd]; carbon 13 p; list of books and periodicals received formic. (Box 27)
  - 1947 July & Oct; newspaper clippings on communists and anti-communism. (Box 27)
  - 1947 Aug 30; printed and typed 1 p; certificate designating 7$rCM United States delegate to the Inter-American Statistical Institute General Assembly. (Box 27)
  - 1947 Dec 28; typed ms 3 p; carbon 8 p; typed 8 p; carbon 3 p. (2 drafts); Walker Medal acceptance speech at AEA meeting. (Box 27)
  - 1948 Apr 2; mimeograph 5 p; quotes from WCM "Quantitative Analysis in Economic Theory" and TV CM note on permission to quote given to Wilson Gee. (Box 27)
  - 1948 May [?]; AZA description of Francis A. Walker Award (from Proceedings) (Box 27)
  - 1948 Oct 29 to Dec 4; 13 newspaper clippings on WCM death (Box 27)
  - carbon ms 14 p; "Wages and Productivity" [reply to G. Soule]. (Box 27, Folder X8)
  - hol 1 p; "controlling Factors in Economic: Situation - Constants or Slowly Changing Variables (Box 27)
  - Printed 4 p; program of inauguration of New School's Institute of World Affairs (WCM speaking on "Economics in a Unified World") (Box 27)
  - hol 3 p; excerpt copy 1 p; "Notes for Discussion of Haney's Paper on C[ost] of Production] Statistics". (Box 27, Folder X4)
  - Carbon ms 4 p; "Coal: a Suggestion for a Hard winter" [by WCIJ?] (Box 27, Folder X12)
  - printed 2 p; program leaf of Little Red School House (lists WCM as trustee) (Box 27, Folder X5)
  - printed 1 p; poem, "Procul Negatus" [By ?."&!?] (Box 27, Folder X7)
  - printed; 26 students' class cards for Economics 315. (Box 27, Folder X15)
  - [1927 or 1923?]; "Amalgamated Plan for Unemployment Insurance". (Box 27, Folder X3)
  - [1940 or later]; carbon ms 6 p; copy 6 p; "Conservation or Liberty". (Box 27, Folder X2)
  - [1940 or later]; carbon ins 1 p; copy 1 p; "Characteristics of the Ordinary Citizen" (Box 27, Folder X1)
  - [1941 or later?]; "Responsibilities of the Directors and Staff of the National Bureau of Economic Research. (Box 27, Folder X9)
  - Miscellaneous (typewritten articles, autograph notes) (Box 41)
  - Calendar (Box 42)
  - Duplicates (Box 43)
  - Notebooks (Box 44)
  - Photographs, Printed Materials. Gift of the University of Connecticut, 30 September 1998 Papers of W. C. Mitchell assembled by Lucy Sprague Mitchell after his death for use in writing her joint biography: 7\vo lives: the story of Wesley Clair Mitchell and myself (New York, Simon and Schuster, 1953) (Box 45)
- Series X: Wesley Clair Mitchell 1998 Addition, (4 Boxes: Boxes 46-49)
  - Subseries X.1: Correspondence
    - Correspondence to & from Mitchell: (Box 46)
      - Anderson, Martha, 3 Aug 1948 ' (Box 46)
      - Angell, James WH 1936-1940 (Box 46)
      - Babst, Dean V, 11 Aug 1947 (Box 46)
      - Barnard, Chester Irving, 12 April 1948 (Box 46)
      - Bass, Robert Perkins, Sept-Nov 1947 (Box 46)
      - Bergeron, Lorenzo U., 14 July 1948 (Box 46)
      - Bezanson, Anne, 14 Jan 1947 (Box 46)
      - Bonbright, James Cummings, 21 Jan 1948 (Box 46)
      - Burgess, Warren Randolph, 10 Nov 1947 (Box 46)
      - Burns, Arthur Frank, 1927-1948 (Box 46)
      - Burns, Eveline Mabel, Dec 1937 (Box 46)
      - Cable, J. Ray, July-Aug 1948 (Box 46)
      - Canby, Henry Seidel, Feb 1948 (Box 46)
      - Carson, William J., 1947-1948 (Box 46)
      - Copeland. Morris Albert 3 Oct 1946 (Box 46)
      - Cowles, Alfred, 3rd, 1936-1937 (Box 46)
      - Crane, Robert Treat, 9 Jan 1937 (Box 46)
      - Crum, Leonard, 8 July 1947 (Box 46)
      - Cummings, John, 9 Oct 1923 (Box 46)
      - Cutler, Addison T., May 1937 (Box 46)
      - Dana, L., 12 June 1936 (Box 46)
      - Davis, Elmer, 17 April 1948 (Box 46)
      - Dewey, John, 5 Dec 1934 (Box 46)
      - Donner, Jane, 3 June 1947 (Box 46)
      - Dorfman, Joseph, 1926-1943 (Box 46)
      - Douglass, Paul F., 4 Dec 1947 (Box 46)
      - Fackenthal, Frank Diehl, 14 April 1937 (Box 46)
      - Fisher, Irving, 1946 (Box 46)
      - Ford, Guy Stanton, March 1935 (Box 46)
      - Fosdick, Raymond Blaine, 18 Jan 1927 (Box 46)
      - G., Charles A, 24 Jan 1938 (Box 46)
      - Gay, Edwin Francis, 1922-1939 (Box 46)
      - Ginzberg, Eli, 10 Feb 1948 & n.d (Box 46)
      - Goodrich, Carter, 11 Nov 1947 (Box 46)
      - Hatfield, Henry R, April-May 1923 (Box 46)
      - Hoover, Herbert, 20 Oct 1934 (Box 46)
      - Hoyt, Homer, 21 Feb 1923 (Box 46)
      - Knauth, Oswald W., 1923-1947 (Box 46)
      - Knight Frank H., March-May 1934 (Box 46)
      - Kuznets, Simon, June 1936 (Box 46)
      - Lewis, Edward, 19 Oct 1937 (Box 46)
      - Lotka, Alfred James, 13 Nov 1947 (Box 46)
      - Lubin, Isador, 19 Nov 1947 (Box 46)
      - Macaulay, Frederick R., 1936-1937 (Box 46)
      - McCrea, Roswell Cheney, 19 March 1937 (Box 46)
      - MacIver, Robert Morrison, 4 June 1936 (Box 46)
      - Masters, Donald Campbell Charles, 1935 (Box 46)
      - May, George O., n.& (Box 46)
      - Means, Gardiner C, 1937-1938 (Box 46)
      - Meeker, Royal, 1921-1948 (Box 46)
      - Mills, Frederick Cecil, 1936-1947 (Box 46)
      - Moore, Geoffrey H., 30 July 1947 (Box 46)
      - Moore, Henry Ludwell, 24 July 19*24 (Box 46)
      - Myrdal, Gunnar, Aug 1947 (Box 46)
      - Nienstaedt, L. R., 1946-1947 (Box 46)
      - Nortman, P. Bernard, 1947-1948 (Box 46)
      - Noyes, C. Reinold, 1947-1948 (Box 46)
      - Ogburn, William Fielding. 5 Feb 1937 (Box 46)
      - Pegram, George Braxton, 1937-1947 (Box 46)
      - Remington, William W, Aug 1948 (Box 46)
      - Rice, Stuart Arthur, July-Oct 1947 (Box 46)
      - Rockefeller, John D., Jr., 13 Feb 1935 (Box 46)
      - Ross, Frank A. 1927-1931 (Box 46)
      - Schultz, Henry, June 1924 (Box 46)
      - Schumpeter, Joseph Alois, 1936-1939 (Box 46)
      - Simkhovitch, Vladimir Gregorievitch, 20 Jan 1939 (Box 46)
      - Smit, Carl Jan, 8 Feb 1947 (Box 46)
      - Smith, J. Russell, 26 Feb 1937 (Box 46)
      - Soule, George, 20 May 1922 (Box 46)
      - Stewart Gertrude D., 17 June 1936 (Box 46)
      - Suranyi-Unger, Theo, 23 Aug 1947 (Box 46)
      - Taylor, Amos E., 24 July 1947 (Box 46)
      - Taylor, Horace, Jan 1931 (Box 46)
      - Thorndike, Lynn, 17 Nov 1937 (Box 46)
      - Turner, Alice Willard, 25 July 1936 (Box 46)
      - Veblen, Thorstein, 1881-1936 copies of corr. & essays by and about T. Veblen. (Box 46)
      - Walker, Sydnor H., 11 Oct 1937 (Box 46)
      - Warren, Robert Beach, 18 July 1947 (Box 46)
      - Weber, Orlando, 4 April 1938 (Box 46)
      - Wilbur, Ray Lyman. 1929-1935 (Box 46)
      - Willcox, Walter Francis, 1947-1952 (Box 46)
      - Willits, Joseph H, 1936-1948 (Box 46)
      - Wilson, Edwin Bidwell, 1928-1948 (Box 46)
      - Wolman, Leo, 25 Aug 1936 (Box 46)
      - Young, Allyn Abbott, Aug 192Young (Box 46)
      - Donald, 7 May 1937 (Box 46)
      - Young, Owen D., 30 March 1935 (Box 46)
  - Subseries X.2: Manuscripts by Mitchell:
    - Diaries: (Box 47)
      - 1904-1911 typescript extracts, 2 tms. (Box 47)
      - 1905-1948 appointment books, 45 vols. (Box 47)
    - Chapter outlines, 1915-1921 & no date (Box 48)
    - Lectures & papers, 1898-1947 & no date (Box 48)
    - National Bureau of Economic Research Incorporated: (Box 49)
    - Memoranda, covering letters, etc., 1947-1948 (Box 49)
    - Printed materials:
      - 1914-1953 (Box 49)